Hello, in this task we are writing the predicate
'penultimate', and we know this needs to be a
binary predicate because of the '\2' here, and
this predicate needs to be such that given a
list 'Xs' and an element 'X', it returns true if
'X' occurs as the penultimate element in the list
'Xs', so the second to last element. We have two
examples here; given the list '[a,b,c,d]' and the
element 'c', it should return true because 'c'
is indeed the second to last element, and given
the list '[a,b,c]' and 'c' should not return true
because now 'c' is not the second to last element,
that would be 'b'. Now what cases do we need to
cover here? Usually, since we are working with a
list of undetermined length, we would first take
a look at the case with the empty list; you could
write this like so... however, this tells Prolog
that given an empty list and a variable X, this
should return true, and this is not what we want
because an empty list doesn't have a penultimate,
so what do we do here? Unlike Haskell, which throws
an error at us if we leave some case undefined,
Prolog doesn't do this; any undefined
case is simply false, and we can
use this to our advantage by just not defining
this case because we would want this to be false.
But I can still work with this because we can
extend this to the next case, which would be a
list with just one element, but once again,
a list with just one element doesn't have a
penultimate element, so we don't want this case to
be true as well. So the next case is the first one
that actually could return true and that would
be a list with two elements; two elements have
a penultimate element which also happens to be the
first element, so we call the first element 'X',
same as our parameter that we're looking for
because these two need to be the same for this
to be true, and the second element in the list we
can just use the underscore because while we need
this to be in here, we're not going to be using
it, so we can basically not assign it to anything.
This just tells it, "Okay, I have a list
with two elements, the first of which
should be the same as my parameter, and if
that's the case, return true", so this is our
first case that can return true. Now
for the next case, obviously, logically that
would be a list with three elements, but
this doesn't really make that much sense, finding
it like this, because while this can be true,
we would then need to define the case for a list
of four elements, and five elements, and so on, and
that's not really practical because we want
to work with lists of any length, so instead
what we're gonna do here is... we already have
a true case; why don't we just use recursion to
reduce down any lists that are longer than that to
eventually get into this case? So we're going to
do this by still taking the first element, and
now we're going to use the pipe character and
call the remaining list Xs; the pipe character
kind of works like the double point in Haskell,
so this tells it this is a list with a first
element and then some remaining list afterwards,
and we define this as only being true when another
call to penultimate, taking this now reduced list,
so the tail, basically, and our parameter X is
true. So we are basically taking the list here
that is NON-EMPTY, throwing the first
element away, and calling penultimate again
on the remaining list. So no matter how long the
list, we are eventually gonna reduce it down to a
case where it's just two elements long, and then
we fall into this case and it can check, "Okay,
is the first element of my two-element list the
same as my parameter?" and if so, return true and
then we get our result, which is exactly what we
want. So this basically already solves our task.
Now we can save this and load it up into a
Prolog prompt, and now we can actually try out
our new predicate here with the examples from the
task description. So I've taken this [a,b,c,d]
and element 'c'; it should return true... and
it does. And given the list [a,b,c] and 'c'
should return false and it does as well so
this is working correctly. Obviously now
this is of course a little boring; this is just
validation, we already know the full list and
we already know the second to last element, so
what else can we do here? We can actually just
change the second parameter to a variable, this
big X here, and then the query is changed to:
"I know the first parameter is a list of
[a,b,c], but I don't know the penultimate;
find me a suitable substitution for X
for which penultimate returns true",
so we're basically now asking Prolog to
find the second to last element for us,
and if we query this, we can see it gets us
X is 'b', which is exactly what we're looking
for. This is the penultimate element and that's
the substitution for the variable that we are
looking for here, and with that it found the second
to last element for us. Now, something else that
we can do, and I'm going to turn trace on for
this so you can see what's actually going on,
is switch this around... let's say we don't know
the list but we know that the second to last
element should be 'a'. Now, we can create this and
then using the trace we can see the first call is
our parameter; this '(_3156)' is a placeholder
value that Prolog uses; whenever you see these
underscores with some number value, this is how
Prolog sees this Xs or whatever variable you've
used and our 'a' that we're looking for, and
then the next step... oh, it's found a list
containing 'a' as the first element and some
other value; this could be anything; this is
another placeholder, but this is basically just
a list with the penultimate element of 'a'
and some other value; this could be anything, and
of course this is our 'a', and then it returns
us this value here, and if we keep doing
this by clicking semicolon, you can see...
it builds us increasingly longer lists;
now this is a list of three elements,
now a list with four elements and so on;
we could keep going like this although it
gets a bit messy with the trace on. So what's
basically going on here is in the first step
it doesn't know the list but it knows our variable
already or what 'X' should be, and then it goes
through all the definitions it has in this rule set
here and it sees, "Okay, the first one tells me"
here's X and here's a list with X in it as well,
so why don't I just make a list with any element,
and the 'X' I already know and give it back?
and then the next step goes one step further
gets into here, makes the recursion call, ends up
here again, and then once again it sees "okay,
that's the X that I already know and this
is the X that needs to be in the list,
so I can build the list", and it takes a step back
on the recursion, adds the elements it moved again
and then that's how it creates the lists longer
than that. So this is pretty useful, now instead
of just having a program that can validate for
us, if we already know the penultimate element,
it can also find the penultimate element for us
or build us lists with the element that we know,
as the penultimate element. Obviously it
doesn't work if we don't know either parameter
that should be pretty clear. Now if
we turn off trace for a moment and
do something else, because one of the interesting
things to consider here is "What happens to all
of this, if we swap these rules around?" Let's
say we thought of the recursion immediately and
the recursion step right away and then we
wrote the final case afterwards, so this
just happened to be how we were thinking about
this. Does this change anything? We save this and
load it up again, and then turn trace back on
again... I turned trace off because it gets kind
of ugly when it loads a file, but that's just an
aside, now you also saw how to turn trace off and
on again. So now with the file reloaded in this
configuration here, let's run our cases again,
so first case the list [a,b,c,d] and 'c', it
should return true. You can walk the trace
here and we can see it's working it out and it
returns true for us. Okay that works, the other
case was [a,b,c], let's see, this should return
false and we can see it working it out again,
and it returns false as well. Now the case of
finding the second to last element for us...
okay, it found X = b our second to last element in
this list again, so this all still works. However
we now use the case where we're looking for
the list itself and looking for any lists with
'a' as the penultimate element... walking through
this let's see... okay taking a little longer,
we just keep going... you can see it never gets
out of this step, if we had trace off we would
eventually get a stack error because it runs out
of stack space, because it keeps going. As you can
see these are all different placeholders, it just
keeps going into the first case so basically it
has some placeholder here for this list, and then
it takes part of that list and calls this again,
then it ends up back in here so we are basically
looping through this first case here and never
getting to the second case, which would be
the only case where it actually sees "Okay,
this is the X I'm looking for and this is
where it should be in the list". So basically
if we order it like this searching for list in
this case doesn't work, because it just keeps
stepping through the first case... and to end
this we actually need to abort this process,
because otherwise it just keeps going until the
stack error, but that takes a little while with
trace on. You can turn trace back off again
for a moment to see what the error looks like
if we run this... and we can see it takes a little
while, and then it tells you 'Out of local stack'
and it keeps doing that, so once again
we abort this. But that was just a little
aside so let's change this back to the correct
configuration here, and this is our task solved!